<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A Blog on Water, Science, Policy, and occasionally Cycling</title>
    <link>/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on A Blog on Water, Science, Policy, and occasionally Cycling</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A Shiny Site for the Upper Oconee Watershed Network</title>
      <link>/2017/03/a-shiny-site-for-the-upper-oconee-watershed-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/a-shiny-site-for-the-upper-oconee-watershed-network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Shiny was first introduced when I was very new to R. I loved the interactive data exploration it offered, and was convinced that proper implementation of Shiny could help further the engagement of &amp;ldquo;citizen scientists&amp;rdquo; and other curious stakeholders (including some of my clients).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to a few years later: I am comfortable with R (though by no means an expert), and in a conversation with a graduate school friend at UGA. She reminds me that a local volunteer group (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uown.org/UOWN-Wordpress/&#34;&gt;UOWN&lt;/a&gt;) regularly collects various water quality data (in fact, I used to process &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; samples for them). However,these data are currently only available to volunteers and other members of the public as an excel file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it would be interesting for the volunteers who collect these data to be able to &amp;ldquo;play around&amp;rdquo; and explore their data. Maybe they are mostly interested in the water quality parameters of the stream that runs behind their house. Maybe they want to know what the trend in conductivity is for the watershed of that stream. A Shiny interface will let them ask and (hopefully) answer these questions. As a bonus, I get to learn a new skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with that in mind, I present &lt;a href=&#34;https://uown.shinyapps.io/test_shiny1/&#34;&gt;my current Alpha shiny site&lt;/a&gt;. I built the site in only a few hours after I figured out the basics of Shiny and reactivity thanks in large part to the guides at &lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com/tutorial/&#34;&gt;Rstudio&lt;/a&gt; and, of course, stackoverflow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;
&lt;!-- /BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;

&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;
&lt;!-- /BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;in-one-sentence&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In one sentence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m an interdisciplinary ecologist in the private sector with a focus on aquatic assessments, microbiology, study design, statistical analysis, and data visualization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;frydenborg-ecologic-llc&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Frydenborg Ecologic, LLC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a background in wetlab bench research. During my undergraduate studies, I was privileged to receive several awards and fellowships that allowed me to conduct research in laboratories while earning my degree. I worked on understanding cellular regulation and developmental biology in both plants and animals. Later I switched focus to the fascinating microscopic world, applying similar molecular methods to understanding the ecology of microbes, and their relationship to human and ecosystem health. Although I enjoyed being a part of basic research, I decided to leave academia due to the uncertain job market, as well as feeling rather burned out by the grind and hours that banging your head against the frontier of knowledge entails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve long been a proponent of science-based policies and evidence-based decision making, and saw an opportunity to engage in this process in a meaningful way by starting a consulting company, Frydenborg Ecologic. I started the company along with my dad in 2014, and I now find myself working at the intersection of policy and science. Our company has worked with private and public stakeholders on projects concerning Numeric Nutrient Criteria, Environmental Resource Permitting, Waste Water Treatment Facility permits, NPDES compliance, Microbial Source Tracking, policy reviews and meta-analyses, and ecological restoration. I find the work consistently interesting, challenging, and rewarding. I get to work on complex problems that have time and resource restraints, clear consequence and impact, and controversy driven by non-scientific ideology. There are very few boring days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can visit the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.frecologic.com/&#34;&gt;company website here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;education&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Education&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.S., Environmental Health Science University of Georgia, 2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thesis: Preliminary analysis of the viral influence on the holobiont of Elkhorn coral, &lt;em&gt;Acropora palmata&lt;/em&gt;, in the context of temperature associated white pox disease&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B.S., Microbiology and Cell Science University of Florida, 2010&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;relavent-skills&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Relavent Skills&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R/Rstudio, QGIS, GRASS, SAGA, Scientific Diving, FDEP Stream Condition Index, FDEP Habitat Assessment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;section&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Finally Built a Blog</title>
      <link>/2017/03/i-finally-built-a-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/i-finally-built-a-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I finally did it. I actually made a blog. The focus of this blog will be things I am familiar with and passionate about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The intersection of science and policy as it relates to water.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploration of the science and evidence behind controversial topics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cycling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll likely deviate from this theme on occassion, but will try to keep the focus there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, here is some test R code so I make sure things are working alright:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017-03-08-hello-world-rmd_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>