<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on A Blog on Water, Science, Policy, and occasionally Cycling</title>
    <link>/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on A Blog on Water, Science, Policy, and occasionally Cycling</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Human Health Criteria</title>
      <link>/2017/03/human-health-criteria/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/human-health-criteria/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;
&lt;!-- /BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;

&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;
&lt;!-- /BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently in Florida, there was some controvery over an update the Florida Department of Environmental Protection (FDEP) promulgated concerning acceptable levels of carcinogens in ambient water and seafood. Most notably, many environmental activists were concerned about historic numbers previously set that were proposed to increase. Many blamed FDEP’s use of a probablistic model instead of the previously used determanistic model, and this theme was repeated in the press:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example article&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example article&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example article&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some environmental activists made claims concerning the validity of the methodology used to derive the updated criteria, claiming that it resulted in much higher levels of toxins than were acceptable. Others asserted that there was in fact “no safe level” for any chemical in the environment (link to that dumbass ron saff).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I’ll attempt to briefly (and almost certaintly incompletely) examine the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the methods used to set standards for human health criteria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How were criteria traditionally set (aka the determanistic approach)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a probablistic approach?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is a probableistic model appropriate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the difference in the acceptable level of a pollutant given by the two approaches?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do other assumptions change the standard?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper will address the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;how were the original numbers determined? This question will address the assumptions made and the model used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;what would the determanstic number be with the new data used for it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;what is the difference in risk between the two numbers?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;import-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Import Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;clean-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Clean Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;compare-determanistic-vs-probablistic-methods-for-one-parameter&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Compare determanistic vs probablistic methods for one parameter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Shiny Site for the Upper Oconee Watershed Network</title>
      <link>/2017/03/a-shiny-site-for-the-upper-oconee-watershed-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/a-shiny-site-for-the-upper-oconee-watershed-network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Shiny was first introduced when I was very new to R. I loved the interactive data exploration it offered, and was convinced that proper implementation of Shiny could help further the engagement of &amp;ldquo;citizen scientists&amp;rdquo; and other curious stakeholders (including some of my clients).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to a few years later: I am comfortable with R (though by no means an expert), and in a conversation with a graduate school friend at UGA. She reminds me that a local volunteer group (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uown.org/UOWN-Wordpress/&#34;&gt;UOWN&lt;/a&gt;) regularly collects various water quality data (in fact, I used to process &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; samples for them). However,these data are currently only available to volunteers and other members of the public as an excel file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it would be interesting for the volunteers who collect these data to be able to &amp;ldquo;play around&amp;rdquo; and explore their data. Maybe they are mostly interested in the water quality parameters of the stream that runs behind their house. Maybe they want to know what the trend in conductivity is for the watershed of that stream. A Shiny interface will let them ask and (hopefully) answer these questions. As a bonus, I get to learn a new skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with that in mind, I present &lt;a href=&#34;https://uown.shinyapps.io/test_shiny1/&#34;&gt;my current Alpha shiny site&lt;/a&gt;. I built the site in only a few hours after I figured out the basics of Shiny and reactivity thanks in large part to the guides at &lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com/tutorial/&#34;&gt;Rstudio&lt;/a&gt; and, of course, stackoverflow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Finally Built a Blog</title>
      <link>/2017/03/i-finally-built-a-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/i-finally-built-a-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I finally did it. I actually made a blog. The focus of this blog will be things I am familiar with and passionate about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The intersection of science and policy as it relates to water.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploration of the science and evidence behind controversial topics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cycling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll likely deviate from this theme on occassion, but will try to keep the focus there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, here is some test R code so I make sure things are working alright:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017-03-08-hello-world-rmd_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>