<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Beck Frydenborg</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Beck Frydenborg</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Beck Frydenborg</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Upper Oconnee Water Network</title>
      <link>/project/shiny_uown_app/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/shiny_uown_app/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Shiny was first introduced when I was very new to R. I loved the interactive data exploration it offered, and was convinced that proper implementation of Shiny could help further the engagement of &amp;ldquo;citizen scientists&amp;rdquo; and other curious stakeholders (including some of my clients).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to a few years later: I am comfortable with R (though by no means an expert), and in a conversation with a graduate school friend at UGA. She reminds me that a local volunteer group (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uown.org/UOWN-Wordpress/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UOWN&lt;/a&gt;) regularly collects various water quality data (in fact, I used to process &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; samples for them). However,these data are currently only available to volunteers and other members of the public as an excel file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it would be interesting for the volunteers who collect these data to be able to &amp;ldquo;play around&amp;rdquo; and explore their data. Maybe they are mostly interested in the water quality parameters of the stream that runs behind their house. Maybe they want to know what the trend in conductivity is for the watershed of that stream. A Shiny interface will let them ask and (hopefully) answer these questions. As a bonus, I get to learn a new skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with that in mind, I present &lt;a href=&#34;https://uown.shinyapps.io/test_shiny1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my current Alpha shiny site&lt;/a&gt;. I built the site in only a few hours after I figured out the basics of Shiny and reactivity thanks in large part to the guides at &lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com/tutorial/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rstudio&lt;/a&gt; and, of course, stackoverflow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
